There's a popular amino acid that's
considered non-essential because our
body produces it. Therefore, it's not
essential to consume. But when our
health is failing, this very same
non-essential amino acid may be drained
from the body. So, could it become more
important to supplement with it? I'm
talking about the amino acid at glycine.
And like I alluded, poor health like
fatty liver disease is believed to rob
the body of glycine as mentioned here.
However, a recent study indicates that a
two-week experiment using glycine may
relieve the liver of disease. Now, if we
look at the blood glycine levels in
animals fed a western diet causing poor
health, including the progression to
liver disease, we can compare the blood
amino acids listed on the left there
between the healthy and unhealthy. If
the color is more blue, that means that
there's reduced amounts of those amino
acids in the blood in the unhealthy. And
if it's red, well, then there's more.
And clearly, glycine at the very end
there is significantly reduced. This
speaks to the possibility that our
glycine levels could be drained. But
there's more to it than that. Because
when we look at evidence in humans,
there's a lot of corroborating evidence.
For example, in the same study, we're
looking at different synthesized sources
of glycine. So, aside from consuming
glycine directly, our body can produce
it from the amino acid thrienine. and
from the molecule sarcasene or from the
amino acid seririne in what's known as a
reversible reaction. Now if we briefly
return to our first data, notice how
seririne and thriionine are both
elevated in the blood. This could be a
signature that they are not being
converted to glycine considering that
glycine is simultaneously low. But
that's three. If we return to the
pathway, you'll notice that there is a
fourth gioxilate.
This is the focus here because glycine
is converted to gioxilate by this DAO
enzyme which is D amino acid oxidase
when introduced at galas. So an already
low glycine pool from a lack of
conversion from thrienine and serarine
is further diminished by DAO. Remember
this is in humans. Finally, what about
the replenishment of glycine? Well, as
you can see in blue, there's this AGXT1
enzyme announced as sir alanine
gioxilate amot transansferase at the
gala. And this enzyme converts our
gioxilate back to glycine.
Unfortunately, what this graph is
telling us beyond just detailing the
pathways that contribute to the glycine
pool is that the enzyme that diminishes
the glycine pool, DAO, is more active
and the replenishment enzyme, AGXT1,
is less active. The main point that I'm
trying to get across here is that we
have multiple possible reasons for why
glycine is low in people and animals
with fatty liver disease and possibly
poor health in general. Now in short
less is being produced through its
various production pathways and more is
being taken out of the glycine pool by
these enzymes. So that sets the stage
for this relationship though associative
that glycine may be a bigger player than
we might think in disease. Still to
actually prove that we can return to
animals and cause gene deletions which
can be simply just cutting out the
genes. in this case, the very same AGXT1
gene. That means that the liver no
longer has the ability to replenish its
glycine stores through this gioxilate
pathway. And sure enough, when we look
at the fatty liver disease score, the
higher the dots, the worse the liver
health, we see that the knockout on the
right and the liver is still able to
replenish glycine on the left. Clearly,
there's a difference. And we're only
talking about eliminating this one
pathway, not touching the other three.
The point here is that we're not only
seeing associations between glycine
pathways and liver disease, we're seeing
a direct cause of worsening liver health
if glycine pathways are not intact. Then
when glycine is supplemented directly,
we also see significant improvements in
liver disease. But we've been focused on
animal research to tease out these
specifics. So what about this 2 week
glycine experiment? What can we take
away based on this newest study in
humans? Well, for one, if you're looking
for how glycine enacts this protective
effect on the liver, or a new peptide
that's built out of glycine that is
supposed to be better than glycine
alone, or where to get reputable sources
of glycine and actually all molecules
that I cover, or learn some of the
additional effects of glycine, then
check out the extended video of the one
that you're currently watching. It's
included for all physionic insiders
along with an accompanying article,
shortened summary of the high-level
points, a podcast, and much more. It's
all listed right here, though even this
list is missing some of the perks.
Anyway, you can join the Physionic
Insiders using the link in the
description. This study did a two-week
experiment where the researchers
measured liver health before and after
merely two weeks of glycine
supplementation. We could see that
transformed here. The higher the bars
are, the worse the liver health. After
only two weeks, liver health improved,
confirmed statistically. Plus, other
liver measures also showed the same
relationship. This tells us that glycine
improves liver health rapidly and
independent of fat loss, which is a big
mover in liver health. Now, keep in mind
that this is a small study and although
it is in humans, which is great, there's
no control group and these people are
obese. So, would these results hold up
when compared against, I don't know, a
placebo group? Would this hold up in
people who aren't overweight yet have
liver disease? These are the kinds of
questions that should hold us back from
being overly definitive. More data is
absolutely needed, even if this is a
strong first step. This would be an
incredibly simple experiment to run on
yourself, though. If you have elevated
liver markers like A and ALT, you could
simply supplement with glycine at the
dose used in the study, which was
actually incredibly high, FYI, around
100 mg per kilogram of body weight, and
then measure again 2 weeks later to
compare. Now, fortunately, glycine is
rather appetizing with a slightly sweet
taste, so you won't have flashbacks of
your parents forcing you to finish
broccoli on your plate. We're talking
early, somewhat speculative evidence
that our glycine pool takes a hit when
we're chronically sick. In this case,
the liver and supplementing may correct
the extremely tax pathways that suck up
glycine. But there are many other areas
of glycine research that I've covered in
the past. If you're interested, then
check them out right here. As always, I
hope you found this as fascinating as I
did. Thanks for nerding out with me.
I'll catch you in the next one. Yes.
Okay. I'll take your I'll take your
silence as a yes in this instance.